<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Walter Scott to Maria Edgeworth, May 15 and 16, 1818 <!--Recipient Name, Month Day, YYYY--></title>
                <author>Maria Edgeworth</author>
                <editor ref="Id_who">
                    Eliza Alexander Wilcox<!--Editor on the Maria Edgeworth Letters Project overseeing the coding of this particular letter: FirstName LastName -->
                </editor>
                <sponsor>
                    <orgName>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</orgName>
                </sponsor>
                <sponsor>Wake Forest University, University of Tennessee, Xavier University, Texas
                    A&amp;M University</sponsor>
                <principal>Jessica Richard, Hilary Havens, Robin Runia, Susan Egenolf</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName ref="Id_who">Eliza Alexander Wilcox<!--FirstName LastName-->
                    </persName>
                    <!-- List all transcribers or coders here, editors and students alike, <persName> by <persName>.-->
                    <persName ref="Id_who"><!--FirstName LastName--></persName>
                    <!-- If you're the last person interacting with the file, enter your name last on the list -->
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: October 24, 2023<date when="2023-10-24">
                    <!--enter the date on which the first coder created and saved this XML file in google drive-->
                </date>
                </edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName type="naf" ref="Id_who">
                        <!--who digitized the letter or gave us permission for to use the file?-->
                    </orgName>
                    <resp> photos include:
                        Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15_page01.jpg
                        Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15_page02.jpg
                        Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15_page03.jpg
                        Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15_page04.jpg<!-- Make a comma-separated list of each .jpg photo file name associated with your letter. 
                     For example: DSCF9476.jpg, DSCF9477.jpg, DSCF9478.jpg-->
                    </resp>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</authority>
                <date>2022</date>
                <availability>
                    <!--Uncomment the appropriate line, based on the archive that holds the physical copy of this letter, 
                  and delete the other comment line(s).-->
                    <p><!--Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.-->
                        <!--or -->
                        <!--Courtesy of <orgName ref="#Rylands">The University of Manchester</orgName>.-->
                    </p>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence>
                </availability>
                <idno>Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15<!--Change to match the file name and current naming standards, i.e. "Edgeworth_Beinecke_330_1817_01_24" if file name is "Edgeworth_Beinecke_330_1817_01_24.xml"--></idno> 
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</title>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en">
                    <!-- This section of the header identifies the original manuscript source. -->
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                        <collection><!-- Enter specific archival collection if applicable--></collection>
                        <idno><!--Consult library or WorldCat for this info--></idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    
                    <!-- FROM LAURA: it's here (below) in the head that I added the full information about the author,
                  and you could add full information about the addressee as well. -->
                    <head>Letter from 
                        <persName xml:id="EdgeM1" from="1768" to="1849">
                            <forename>Maria</forename>
                            <surname>Edgeworth</surname>
                            <date>1768-1849</date>
                            <idno type="VIAF">71477273</idno>
                            <idno type="SNAC">62567029</idno>
                        </persName>
                        to <persName><!--Recipient Name--></persName>, <placeName><!--Location where letter was sent--></placeName>, 
                        <date when="1111-01-01"><!-- Transcribe the date as it appears on the letter itself. Enter a numeric standardized date value in @when. --></date>
                    </head>
                    <physDesc>
                        <!-- optional physical description of the letter goes here: paper size and condition, seal, postmarks, etc.-->
                    </physDesc>
                </msDesc>
                
                <!-- FROM LAURA: where to put the following information in <bibl> is still a question: 
               ask TEI List whether it should be in the sourceDesc or elsewhere? -->
                
                <bibl>In addition to our edited version, this letter was previously published in
                    <!--complete bibiographical info if letter was published in a book here - if not delete-->
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <!--Where Edgeworth uses nonstandard spelling and hyphenation of words, transcriber-coders 
               should use TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Edgeworth’s 
               spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, 
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. -->
                <p>Edgeworth’s spelling and punctuation are retained in transcription, except where a
                    word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in a manuscript. The
                    long s and ligatured forms are silently emended.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                <correspAction type="sent">
                    <persName><!--SENDER NAME--></persName>
                </correspAction>
                <correspAction type="received">
                    <persName><!--RECIPIENT NAME--></persName>
                </correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2021-01-01" who="Id_who">
                <!--Brief description of what you did here.-->
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter">
                <pb n="1" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15_page01.jpg"/>
                <!--filenames for photos associated with this letter. Example: <pb n="1" facs="image1.jpg image2.jpg image3.jpg"/> -->
                <opener>
                    <dateline><!--If there's no date line, omit this element. Record in the order in which it is written on the letter.-->
                        <name type="place" ref="Id_where"/>
                        <date when="1818-05-15"/>15 May 1818</dateline>
                    <salute>
                        <persName>
                            <!-- Use if letter has a saluation ("Dear Sir," for example). If not, delete this line.-->
                        </persName>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p> <note place="bottom">3x</note>
                    I lost no time my dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Miss Edgeworth</persName> in complying with your
                    wishes. But I regret to say that as yet I have not found <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeR1">Mr Edgeworths</persName>
                    favour on the subject you mention. It must be in existence as I am sure I
                    never would destroy any trace of a correspondence by which I esteem
                    myself so much honoured. I only arrived in town last night having
                    received your letter amongst my infant woods at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Abbotsford-House_STK">Abbotsford</placeName> and <choice><orig>com
                        menced</orig><reg>commenced</reg></choice> my researches this morning. My papers are but very imperfectly
                    arranged considering that I was bred to business but in 1811 I perceive
                    I had been already favoured with several letters from the late regretted
                    <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeR1">Mr. E</persName> <del></del> <add>three</add>of which I inclose for the chance of their containing <choice><orig>some
                        thing</orig><reg>something</reg></choice> interesting to your present labours of love. The letter <choice><orig>concern
                            ing</orig><reg>concerning</reg></choice> <persName ref="./Personography.xml#DarwE1">Darwin</persName> must I think be among a mass of papers relating to
                    <persName ref="./Personography.xml#SeweA1">Miss Sewards</persName> poems which I will make a thorough search amongst
                    as soon as may be. I assure you dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Madam</persName> there is no person
                    in the world of literature for whose name <unclear>I have</unclear> more sincere respect
                    or in whose regard I esteem myself more highly honoured, or whom I
                    would have more pleasure in obliging. You have had a merit <choice><orig>transcend
                        dent</orig><reg>transcendent</reg></choice> in my eyes of raising your national character in the scale of
                    public estimation and making the <unclear>men</unclear> of the British empire acquainted
                    with the peculiar and interesting character of a people too long <choice><orig>neglec
                        -ted</orig><reg>neglected</reg></choice> and too severely oppressed. Public opinion though a slow is at
                    length a sure <unclear>rebuffer</unclear> of wrongs and when this in respect to <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#IE">Ireland</placeName>
                    you have produced a strong and abiding affect and I trust that
                    notwithstanding all the unfavourable circumstances which seem
                    fated to restart the amelioration of Ireland I cannot help thinking
                    that writings which back its natives their force and their weakness
                    and shew to their fellow subjects there that value and worth must
                    prepare both for a gradual but happy change. I do not rate the <choice><orig>un
                        -known</orig><reg>unknown</reg></choice> author of our Scottish tales so high as to place him in the same <add>rank</add>
                    either of <unclear>Morel or utility</unclear>and yet I think highly of many of his
                    works and expect to be gratified by those which are still promised
                    from the same abundant and concealed source. I do assure you
                    
                    <pb n="2" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1818_05_15_page02.jpg"/>
                    
                    I am quite an impartial judge upon the occasion &amp; that you do me
                    too much honour in supposing that I have any interest in these <choice><orig>nar
                        -ratives</orig><reg>narratives</reg></choice>. The whole story told (as <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BailJ1">Miss Baillie</persName> informed me) by a Sir
                    somebody Gordon about my having intimated to him any acquiescence
                    in the report of my being the author of <del></del> <title ref="./Workography.xml#Antiq1">Antiquary</title> is so absolutely
                    false that I do not even know such a person I <hi rend="underline">did</hi> know Sir Alis[superscript]t[/superscript].
                    Gordon who fell gloriously at Waterloo &amp; I <hi rend="underline">do</hi> know Sir Alexander
                    Gordon of [unclear]Hilvenum[/unclear] but no other of the name. So if the Knight swears
                    by his honour that the pancakes are naught do you eat the <choice><orig>pan
                        cakes</orig><reg>pancakes</reg></choice> tout de meme &amp; do not rashly suppose the Chevalier <unclear>forsworn</unclear>
                    if you should find them very good. All this however I wrote to M[superscript]rs[/superscript]
                    Baillie I should rather say to our dear Joanna whose talents and [unclear]heart[/unclear]
                    you I know hold as highly as I do; so that I suppose she has already
                    written to you on that subject. [paragraph ends]
                    
                    Abbotsford 16 May 
                    It was destined I was not to find the letter until I returned hither for
                    an unfortunate partiality for little cabinets and great cabinets and
                    all sort of concealments and pigeon-holes holes makes it very difficult for me
                    to know where any particular paper may happen to be [unclear][/unclear] I regret that
                    the delay this has occasioned may make me seem what I would most
                    unwillingly be thought slack or careless in complying with your request
                    The letter contains an excellent and animated defence of D[superscript]r[/superscript] Darwin written
                    with the spirit and feeling which your late respected relative was most
                    likely to have exerted in behalf of a freind. Still however it does not
                    appear to me to shake the powerful evidence that the lines in dispute
                    were claimed by Miss Seward during Doctor Darwins lifetime and pub
                    lished as hers and with her name. After all I do not think the verses
                    very much were worth struggling about. But the liberality of the letter does great
                    honour (like everything thing he did) to Mr. E.s memory. I found in the same
                    drawer a letter of my own to Mr. Edgeworth begun after my release from
                    France and never finished: a memorial among too many others how
                    often I am misled by an unfortunate habit of procrastination into beco
                    ming indifferent to the kindness of my best friends. Latterly indeed that
                    as for the last twelve months I have had very indifferent health to plead as
                    an excuse for being an irregular correspondent. I begin within these
                    two last months to feel like myself again so that I trust I shall not
                    have that painful apology any longer.[paragraph ends]
                    
                    [page 3] 
                    
                    I am much obliged to you for thinking favourably of my attempts in poetry
                    They have one title to indulgent compassion which is that they are a sort of or-
                    phans for whom their ostich-parent cares most exceedingly little. In the earlier
                    part of my literary life partly from temper partly from principle having observed
                    how very unhappy library persons are made (not to say ridiculous into the bar-
                    gain) by pitching their thoughts and happiness upon popular fame that I resolved
                    to avoid at least that frailty & think as little about my poems when committed
                    to the public as I well could. It is only when you Miss Edgeworth or a few others
                    whose talents & candour rank high with me are kind enough to say that you
                    receive pleasure from these poems that I ever think of them with satisfaction or
                    indeed [insertion]think of them[/insertion] at all. I have not read one of them since they were printed excepting
                    last year the Lady of the Lake which I liked better than I expected but not
                    well enough to induce me to go through the rest so I may truly say with
                    I am afraid to think of what I've done
                    Macbeth
                    I am afraid to think of what I've done
                    Look out again I dare not -
                    This much of Macbeth I recollect for that is not so easily forgotten that
                    she was attempted from the existing person & character of a lady who is now
                    no more. So that I am particularly flattered with your distinguishing it
                    from the others which are in general mere shadows. [paragraph ends]
                    
                    Thus far [underline]have I written amidst the clank and clang produced by [/underline]
                    two noisy young bachelors my son and a cousin who are wearing out a rainy
                    day by fencing with their naked broadswords to the imminent peril of
                    their own heads to animate which conflict a probationary piper is excercizing
                    a new & not over well tuned pair of bagpipes - all this being literally the
                    case I really hardly know whether I am writing sense or nonsense - At
                    least I must be comforted with the idea that my family is making
                    some noise in the world [paragraph ends]
                    
                    My rustic employments are so numerous and require so much of my
                    own eye that I have no thoughts this season of quitting Scotland.
                    If I can get away in winter I should like much to see Italy but I fear
                    I cannot do this very conveniently. Ireland I trust I will one day visit
                    but I must first get my dominions here put into some sort of orders
                    I have of late been rather an extensive planter and incline in
                    proportion to the extent of my property and these operations require
                    a good deal of personal superintendence. [pagagraph ends]
                    
                    A clergyman in your neighbourhood by name a gallant Gra-
                    ham applied to me some time since wishing to connect himself with
                    the border tribe of that name & willing to forward so reasonable & lau-
                    dable a request I did some time since communicate to him what
                    information occured to my recollection concerning these [unclear]worthies[/unclear]
                    
                    He now writes to me that you wish to have a copy which (though I [unclear]should[/unclear]
                    think it very uninteresting to you) is of course most humbly at your
                    service. As however it was merely intended to gratify his own curiosity
                    & by no times designed as a genealogical history for which I have neither
                    time/ materials nor inclination - I hope the reverend gentleman will
                    not take any means forgiving to the public such crude lucubrations,
                    I do not know any thing of M[superscript]r [/superscript]Graham but I am always willing to
                    return a civil answer to a gentleman of his profession who writes to me
                    civilly; only I dont like to be hooked in for appearances on the
                    public stage of which I have already made too many.</p>
                <closer>
                    Adieu my dear Miss Edgeworth My best wishes attend you
                    in public & private & if we should never meet I trust you will still
                    believe that you have not a more sincere friend and well wisher
                    than Walter Scott.
                    15 May 1818<!--include linebreaks, if used. example: <closer> Yours<lb/> Very sincerely<lb/> -->
                </closer>
                <postscript>
                    I shall send these packet to my official friend Croker to be
                    put under one of his omnipotent franks.
                    
                    [other hand]113. 15
                    [underline]3[/underline]
                    341 . 5
                    W. Scott. May 15. 1818[/other hand]<p><!--A postscript goes here, outside the <closer>. --></p>
                </postscript>
                <!--You can include a <pb/> here, or inside the postScript.-->
                <!-- Format for postscripts. 
               Postscripts do NOT go inside closer tags. Adjust to take into account the order in your letter. 
               Sometimes the signature is on page three, the address on page four, then the postscript follows back on the top of page one, for example.-->
                <closer><!--Use the <closer> element again to hold Address Leaf information.-->
                    <address>
                        <!--Include any text written on the address leaf; use a separate "addrLine" for each line and indicate line breaks. -->
                        <addrLine/>
                        <addrLine/>
                        <addrLine/>
                    </address>
                </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back> </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
