<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Maria Edgeworth to Mrs. Griffith, April 20, 1826</title>
            <author>Maria Edgeworth</author>
            <editor ref="Id_who">Alexandra LaGrand</editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>Wake Forest University, University of Tennessee, Xavier University, Texas
               A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Jessica Richard, Hilary Havens, Robin Runia, Susan Egenolf</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="Id_who">Alexandra LaGrand</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2024-01-11">January 11, 2024</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <orgName ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82003163">Princeton University Library</orgName>
               <resp> photos include: Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page01.jpg, Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page02.jpg, Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page03.jpg, Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page04.jpg 
               </resp>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</authority>
            <date>2022</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of <orgName ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82003163">Princeton University Library</orgName></p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0) Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno>Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04</idno> 
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Princeton University Library</repository>
                  <collection></collection>
                  <idno></idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from 
                  <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">
                     <forename>Maria</forename>
                     <surname>Edgeworth</surname>
                  </persName>
                   to <persName>Mrs. Griffith</persName>, <placeName></placeName>, 
                  <date when="1826-04-20">April 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1826</date>
               </head>
               <physDesc></physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Edgeworth’s spelling and punctuation are retained in transcription, except where a
               word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in a manuscript. The
               long s and ligatured forms are silently emended.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Maria Edgeworth</persName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName>Mrs. Griffith</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-04-20" who="Id_who">Created file for letter, encoded letter</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page01.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place" ref="Id_where"/>Edgeworths Town
                  <date when="1826-04-20"/>April 20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1826</dateline>
               <salute>
                  <persName>Dear M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Griffith</persName>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have made many attempts but have not
               yet succeeded in collecting means of an-
               swering the various questions and interest
               ing subjects of discussion in your last kind
               letter - I have shown the very pretty and
               useful &amp; ingenious model of your beehive
               to all whom it might concern in my neighbor
               hood - I cannot say that there any among
               our neighbors who deserve to be called <hi rend="underline">apiarists</hi>
               <del>as</del> they have none of them a sufficient num-
               ber of beehives or sufficient experience - But
               they have sense enough to see the value of your
               <unclear>b</unclear>ee hive and I am sure it will be imitated
               successfully. - I have sent, through Lord Oriel
               a description of it in your own &amp; in M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>. Balstones
               words to the Horticultural Society at Kew
               and have waited with too great patience for
               their acknowledgment and for their reply
               to your observations on boring which I also
               copied for them - From another friend
               who has experience on the subject I also <hi rend="underline">ex</hi>
               pect some information &amp; from my brother
               William hope for some when he returns home
               - but he is at present absence &amp; engaged so much
               professionally that he has scarcely time to write
               the shortest letters home
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page02.jpg"/>
               The situation of Sir Walter Scott's affairs <del>has</del>
               and my knowing how very busy he has been have
               prevented me from yet forwarding to him the
               copy of Mr. Bryant's poems which you sent me
               for him - but I will do so now that he is more
               at leisure and that I see <hi rend="underline">Woodstock</hi> is out - as
               this days paper informs me - You will be glad
               to hear that his losses are not so great as report
               made them - He has lost about 30,000 Sterling
               - but Abbotsford and his library - and his tem-
               per - and his gaité de coeur are all safe -
               One question of yours I can answer -
               Why did Sir Walter Scott not mention Miss Austin
               in his lives of the British novellists <hi rend="underline"><add>Not</add></hi> Because
               <add>he undervalued her talents - of that he is incapable - But simply because</add>
               the work was continued only to the time of Cum-
               berland whose novels were published many years
               before Miss Austins - The work did not succeed &amp;
               was discontinued - These lives which were <del>intended</del>
               to be prefixed to the works of each of the author were
               never published separately in these countries -
               Galignani had the sense to republish them in
               Paris in his newspaper &amp; then finding how much
               they were admired, published them in two small
               volumes in the form in which they now appear -
               Beautiful specimens of biography &amp; criticism they
               are! - In my opinion fully equal &amp; in some parts
               superior in interest and literary value to D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               Johnson's prefaces. - They are not so dogmatic, and
               they <add>contain</add> <del>are</del> more philosophical criticism - They are
               peculiarly interesting as containing the opinions
               &amp; <unclear><del></del></unclear> letting us into some of the principles of com-
               position of one who has so eminently excelled
               <del>both</del> as a poet, <del>and</del> an inventor &amp; an author
               of fictitious narratives - Johnson can hardly
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page03.jpg"/>
               be called a poet - except a satirical <unclear>poet</unclear> - (See London
               &amp; the Vanity of human wishes - that is all - And as
               for invention, - the only example we have of any
               invention of his is in Rasselas - <del>I have not time</del>
               <del>to</del> - and in that <del><unclear></unclear></del> the insane phi
               losopher who fancied he ruled the weather is
               the only quite new &amp; original invention I can
               recollect of Johnson - As to Scott ~~ who alive
               or dead <add>except Shakespear</add> can stand a comparison with him in
               invention, - the true test of genius
               I am very much afraid that I
               shall never be able to satisfy you about the (<del></del> <add>Last</add> of
               the Mohicans - But it is early times with us
               yet - as we began it only last night and have
               read only 20 pages - Thank you for it however
               my dear Madam at all events - and give me
               credit for my sincerity. If in my next letter when
               we have read the whole I can tell you I like it
               you will have faith in my praises. 
               <add>April 21<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>. Last night we got into the cavern <del>&amp;</del> that is a sublime
               scene - We began to be much interested -</add>
               I merely wrote a few lines to you at present
               to assure you that I am not ungrateful for all your
               kind attentions. The specimens of the ground
               pine and of the festoon pine have delighted me
               and many of my more deserving botanical friends
               - I beg you will not make any more attempts to
               send me sweetmeats - I am quite ashamed! - I am 
               assured that no captain of any vessel will take charge
               of them - except it be a captain of an <add>English</add> man of war or frigate
               -- I have half a mind to beg from you a draught
               or chess board <add>or wash bord</add> to be made of specimens of American
               woods - the beauty of the wood of which your model
               of a beehive was made put this idea into my head &amp; the
               nicety of the workmanship shewed me that your American
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="Edgeworth_Princeton_1826-04_page04.jpg"/>
               workmen can vye with our best cabinetmakers -
               I am very sorry indeed to hear such bad accounts
               of the maddens - But I cannot yet believe that Madden
               has turned out dishonest -- Tho I said I w<hi rend="superscript">d</hi> write only a few lines
               I must <add>write more</add> - I am at this moment in great perplexity - A
               very <add>dear &amp; very</add> amiable - entertaining &amp; <hi rend="underline">improvident</hi> friend of
               mine, long known &amp; long loved by my father &amp; by
               all our family has <add>now</add> just <add>suddenly</add> died &amp; left a widow &amp;
               7 children of all ages from 22 to 10 years old
               absolutely unprovided for - after having lived
               till now in affluence &amp; in the best society in
               this country - The gentleman was a clergyman
               - I am ashamed to confess to you that he had
               a living of eighteen hundred a year - but he
               lived <hi rend="underline">up to it</hi> as we say in this country - M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. J
               every year attempted to lay by something but
               he continually broke in upon her fund - And
               suddenly in the prime of life he was snatched away!
               M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Johnson has been an exemplary wife &amp;
               mother - Her daughters, two of them are <hi rend="superscript">beauti</hi>
               <hi rend="underline">ful</hi> - all <add>of them</add> accomplished &amp; well informed, with
               <hi rend="underline">peculiar natural &amp; acquired</hi> talents <add>vocal &amp; instrumental</add> for music -
               They in the midst of this sudden distress turn
               their minds at once to consider how they can
               assist their mother in supporting themselves inde
               pendantly - It has been suggested that they
               might take a house at Bath &amp; receive two or 3
               unmarried young ladies as lodgers who might
               have the advantage of the protection &amp; society of
               <add>a lady of good family the habits of good company)
               good principles With</add> M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Johnson <unclear>&amp; <add>also</add></unclear> the advantage
               of <del>her</del> musical practice &amp; instruction from herself
               and her daughters should be considered
               Would such a plan succeed in Philadelphia
               - or new york? Could <add>2 or 3</add> boarders be secured who
               could pay 2 hundred a year? Would <add>the</add> young
               ladies be likely to <hi rend="underline">establish</hi> themselves well?               
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back> </back>
   </text>
</TEI>