<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Walter Scott to Maria Edgeworth, April 24, 1822 </title>
            <author>Maria Edgeworth</author>
            <editor>
                    Eliza Alexander Wilcox</editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>Wake Forest University, University of Tennessee, Xavier University, Texas
                    A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Susan Egenolf, Meredith Hale, Hilary Havens, Jessica Richard, and Robin Runia</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Eliza Alexander Wilcox</persName>
               <persName/>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: April 24, 1822<date when="2022-04-24"/>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <orgName type="naf" ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80044899">
                        National Library of Scotland</orgName>
               <resp> photos include:
                        Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24_page01.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24_page02.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24_page03.jpg
                       </resp>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</authority>
            <date>2022</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80044899">National Library of Scotland</orgName>
               </p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0) Unported
            License</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                  <collection/>
                  <idno>Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from 
                        <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW1">Walter Scott</persName>, <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Abbotsford-House_STK">Abbotsford</placeName>, 
                        <date when="1822-04-24">April 24, 1822</date>
                        to <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Maria Edgeworth</persName>, <placeName/>, 
                        <date when="1822-04-24">April 24, 1822</date>
               </head>
               <physDesc/>
            </msDesc>
            <bibl>In addition to our edited version, this letter was previously published in
                    </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Edgeworth’s spelling and punctuation are retained in transcription, including non-standard spelling, line breaks, and hyphenation of words. The long s and ligatured forms are silently emended.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW1">Walter Scott</persName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Maria Edgeworth</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2021-01-01" who="Id_who"/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24_page01.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date when="1111-11-11"/>
               </dateline>
               <salute>
                  <persName>
                            My dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Miss Edgeworth</persName>
                  </persName>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am extremely sorry indeed that you cannot
                    fulfill your kind intentions to be at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Abbotsford-House_STK">Abbotsford</placeName> this year. It is
                    a grievous disappointment and I am grieved to think it should
                    have arisen from the loss of a valued connexion. That is the
                    worst part of life when its <unclear/> path is trod - If my limbs are
                    stiff my walks are shorter and my rides slower if my eyes
                    fail me I can use glasses &amp; a large print if I get a little deaf
                    I comfort myself that except in a few instances I should be
                    no great loser by missing one full half of what is spoken but
                    I feel the loneliness of age when my companions and friends are
                    taken from me. The sudden death of both the Boswells &amp;
                    the bloody end of the last have given me great pain. You have
                    never got <hi rend="underline">half</hi> the praise Vivian ought to have procured you - the <choice>
                  <orig>rea-
                        son</orig>
                  <reg>reason</reg>
               </choice> is that the class from which the excellent portraits are drawn
                    feel the resemblance too painfully to thank the author for it and
                    I do not believe the common readers understand it <unclear>there on</unclear> the least.
                    I who thank God am neither great man nor politician have lived
                    enough among those to recognize the truth and nature of the
                    painting and am no way implicated in the satire. I begin to <del/>
                    think that of the three kingdoms the English alone are qualified
                    to mix in politics safely and without fatal results - the force
                    and hasty resentments of the Irish and the sullen long-enduring
                    revengeful temper of my countrymen makes such agitations
                    have a much wider and more dreadful effect amongst them.</p>
            <p>Well - we will forget what we cannot help and pray that
                we may lose no more friends till in finitas I hope &amp; am sure
                we shall st<unclear/> friends in each other. I had arranged to stay
                at least a week after the 12 of may in hopes of detaining you
                
<pb n="2" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24_page02.jpg"/> 
                  
                at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Abbotsford-House_STK">Abbotsford</placeName> and I will not <unclear>quit</unclear> you under a month or two
                the next year. I shall have my house completed my library <choice>
                  <orig>re-
                    placed</orig>
                  <reg>replaced</reg>
               </choice> - my armoury new furbished - my piper new clothed and
                the time shall be july. I thnk I will have the same family about
                me and perhaps my two sons. <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW2">Walter</persName> is at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Berlin_DE">Berlin</placeName> studying the
                great art of war - he entertains a most military conviction that
                all the disturbances of <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#IE">Ireland</placeName> are exclusively <unclear>owing</unclear> to his
                last regiment the 18.<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>Hussars being imprudently reduced. Little
                  <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotC1">Charles</persName> is striving to become a good scholar and fit for Oxford.
                Both have a chance of being at home in Autumn 1823. I know <choice>
                  <orig>no-
                    thing</orig>
                  <reg>nothing</reg>
               </choice> I would wish you to see which has any <add>particular</add> chance of becoming
                invisible in the course of fourteen months excepting my old bloodhound
                poor fellow on whom age now sits so heavily that he cannot follow
                far from the house - I wished you to see him very much he is of
                that noble breed which <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#IE">Ireland</placeName> as well as <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#STK">Scotland</placeName> are possessed
                and which is now almost extinct in both countries. I know some
                times thought of the final cause of dogs having such short lives
                and I am quite satisfied it is the compassion to the human race
                for if we suffer so much in living a day after an acquaintance
                of ten or twelve years what would it be if they were to live
                double that time.</p>
            <p>I do not propose being in London this year. I do not like
                it - there is such a <unclear>riding</unclear> and <unclear>driving</unclear>- so much to see - so much
                to say - not to mention plovers eggs and champagne - that I
                always feel too much excited in London though it is good to
                rub off the rust too some times &amp; brings you up abreast with the
                world as it goes - </p>
            <p>I must break off being summoned to a conclave to examine
                how the progress of decay which at present threatens to destroy
                the ruins of Melrose can yet be arrested - the advice of the friend
                you have lost would have been invaluable for the matter is
                very delicate. The Duke of Buccleuch however though but a
                boy is very desirous to have something done and his questions
                
                 <pb n="3" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1822_04_24_page03.jpg"/>   
                 
                on the Duke of Buccleuch's offer to <unclear>repair</unclear>
                have acquiesced in a trick so reasonable &amp; creditable to the
                little Chief. I only hope they will be liberal for a trifle will do no
                good or rather I think any partial tampering is likely to
                do harm - but the Duke has an immense estate and I hope
                they will remember that though a moderate sum may keep up
                this national monument yet his whole income could not replace
                it should it fall.</p>
            <closer>
                    Yours dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Miss Edgeworth</persName> with true respect and re
                    -gard
                    <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW">Walter Scott</persName>
               <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Abbotsford-House_STK">Abbotsford Melrose</placeName>
                    24 April 1822</closer>
            <postscript>
               <p/>
            </postscript>
            <closer>
               <address>
                  <addrLine/>
                  <addrLine/>
                  <addrLine/>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back/>
   </text>
</TEI>
