<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Frances Anne Edgeworth to Esther Brinkley, May 9, 1829</title>
            <author>Frances Edgeworth</author>
            <editor>Alexandra LaGrand</editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>Wake Forest University, University of Tennessee, Xavier University, Texas
               A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Susan Egenolf, Meredith Hale, Hilary Havens, Jessica Richard, and Robin Runia</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Alexandra LaGrand</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2024-05-26">May 26, 2024</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <orgName type="naf">National Library of Scotland</orgName>
               <resp> photos include: Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page01.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page02.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page03.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page04.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page05.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page06.jpg</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</authority>
            <date>2022</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80044899">National Library of Scotland</orgName>
               </p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0) Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno>Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                  <collection/>
                  <idno/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from 
                  <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeF2">
                     <forename>Frances Anne</forename>
                     <surname>Edgeworth</surname>
                  </persName>
                  to <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinE1">Esther Brinkley</persName>, <placeName/>, 
                  <date when="1829-05-09">May 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1829</date>
               </head>
               <physDesc/>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Edgeworth’s spelling and punctuation are retained in transcription, including non-standard spelling, line breaks, and hyphenation of words. The long s and ligatured forms are silently emended.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeF2">Frances Anne Edgeworth</persName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinE1">Esther Brinkley</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05-26" who="Id_who">Created file for letter, encoded letter</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page01.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date when="1829-05-09">May 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1829</date>
               </dateline>
               <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Edgeworthstown_IE">Edgeworthstown</placeName>
            </opener>
            <p>
               It was but a few days ago dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinE1">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brinkley</persName>
               <lb/>
               that I was reading over your beautiful and touching<lb/>
               letter on the death of your beautiful and young<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinA1">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>daughter in law</orig>
                     <reg>daughter-in-law</reg>
                  </choice>
               </persName> - little thinking that in two<lb/>
               short weeks I was to call on your feelings again<lb/>
               and open the scarcely closed wounds of your<lb/>
               sorrowing heart by telling you that we have lost<lb/>
               our dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeW1">William</persName> - our dear son I might say with<lb/>
               truth - for though neither you nor I brought him<lb/>
               in to the world he loved &amp; treated us as if we had<lb/>
               been his real mothers - During this fatal illness<lb/>
               his thoughts often recurred to the time when he<lb/>
               was so ill at the <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Dunsink-Observatory_IE">observatory</placeName> when you and the<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinJ1">Bishop</persName> and every one were so kind to him<lb/>
               and often said "dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinE1">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brinkley</persName> my dear other<lb/>
               "mother - do write to her and tell her how ill<lb/>
               "I am and how tenderly and how gratefully I<lb/>
               "think of her" - I did not write because I<lb/>
               still hoped that in a few days I might tell<lb/>
               you of <del>your</del> his illness as of a thing that was past<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page02.jpg"/>
               and only call upon you to rejoice with me<lb/>
               at his convalescence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               The disease was inflammation of the Lungs -<lb/>
               and had I fear taken too fast hold of him<lb/>
               before he returned home for medical art<lb/>
               to save him - The <choice>
                  <orig>skilful</orig>
                  <reg>skillful</reg>
               </choice> surgeon near us<lb/>
               and a physician from <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Dublin_IE">Dublin</placeName> had a bad opinion<lb/>
               of him from the first - they agreed in ordering<lb/>
               repeated bleedings which relieved the cough &amp; pain<lb/>
               but never touched the pulse; it continued from<lb/>
               first to last above a 100 generally 120 -<lb/>
               At first blisters on the chest could not be made<lb/>
               to rise - or even to produce a prickly feeling &amp;<lb/>
               at last when they did rise - the discharge<lb/>
               produced no relief. Yet for two days (monday<lb/>
               &amp; tuesday last) he seemed to mend - and even<lb/>
               on wednesday morning his pulse was a little <unclear>bett</unclear>
               <lb/>
               but that day some most fatal change took place<lb/>
               between my first and second visit to him, which<lb/>
               so altered his looks that I was shocked when<lb/>
               I saw him and from that moment he declined<lb/>
               so rapidly - that no hope could be recalled<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page03.jpg"/>
               twelve hours! I have allowed my pen to <unclear>run</unclear>
               <lb/>
               on more at length to you my dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinE1">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brinkley</persName>
               <lb/>
               than to any one else to whom I have written<lb/>
               for he wished that you and the dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrinJ1">Bishop</persName>
               <lb/>
               should know as much about <add>him</add> as possible<lb/>
               and I know so much of your kind natures<lb/>
               that you will feel sympathy with all of us<lb/>
               for the irreparable loss we have sustained<lb/>
               and forgive me for renewing your own<lb/>
               sorrow by describing ours.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               I think that the all wise disposer of events<lb/>
               will strengthen our bodies - and teach our<lb/>
               minds to receive benefit from this severe<lb/>
               lesson - by preparing each of us for our latter<lb/>
               end and increasing the faith that is in us<lb/>
               that may be worthy servants of Christ and<lb/>
               keep us from murmuring at the decrees of God.<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeW1">William</persName> died at half past 4 on thursday morning the<lb/>
               7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>.! and the grave will soon contain all that<lb/>
               once was him.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page04.jpg"/>
               How closely are life and death brought together! -<lb/>
               On the 5<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> at 3 <choice>
                  <orig>oclock</orig>
                  <reg>o'clock</reg>
               </choice> my dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeS1">Sophy</persName> gave me another<lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>Grandaughter</orig>
                  <reg>granddaughter</reg>
               </choice> - born 14 days before her time - but<lb/>
               both mother and child were doing well when <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeH1">Harriet Butler</persName>
               <lb/>
               who was fortunately with her - wrote to me -<lb/>
               I perceive that I have omitted to mention - that dear<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeW1">William's</persName> head remained perfectly clear - and<lb/>
               though he had so much fever had no tendency<lb/>
               to delirium - but one day - &amp; then only slightly<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page05.jpg"/>
               Dear fellow - he knew us all to the last moment<lb/>
               wished so much that his brother <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeF1">Francis</persName> had been<lb/>
               with him - begged I would not leave him &amp;<lb/>
               died while I held his dear cold hand -<lb/>
               It still appears a frightful dream to me, and<lb/>
               I can hardly persuade myself that I shall never<lb/>
               again hear that affectionate voice; or see those<lb/>
               eyes look upon me again. To me he was a most<lb/>
               kind son - a living image of his dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeR1">father</persName> in<lb/>
               many ways - and most particularly in an<lb/>
               uncompromising honesty and independence<lb/>
               of character which rested on its own integrity;<lb/>
               and <add>also</add> in the incomparable fertility of his <choice>
                  <orig>inven<lb/>
               -tive</orig>
                  <reg>inventive</reg>
               </choice> powers - which continued to the last<lb/>
               and alas, contributed to their own destruction<lb/>
               for it was not possible to enforce the tranquility<lb/>
               that was so necessary. It was not possible to<lb/>
               keep him from inventing, speaking, directing.<lb/>
               How do I now regret the mistaken tenderness<lb/>
               that permitted those exertions - or rather that<lb/>
               I made so unwise a calculation when I thought<lb/>
               the opposing of these exertions would fret &amp; hurry him<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_6931_1829_05_09_page06.jpg"/>
               him more than the letting him get them off<lb/>
               his mind! - Perhaps the end would have been<lb/>
               equally fatal - and he would have been less<lb/>
               comfortable - As it was he frequently said<lb/>
               he felt perfectly happy - that the delight of<lb/>
               being at home surrounded with kind and<lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>sympathising</orig>
                  <reg>sympathizing</reg>
               </choice> friends gave him a degree of <choice>
                  <orig>com<lb/>
               -fort</orig>
                  <reg>comfort</reg>
               </choice> he had been a stranger to for many months -<lb/>
               That he could not call to mind the having willingly<lb/>
               done harm to any human creature - That he<lb/>
               could not reproach himself with having seduced<lb/>
               or corrupted or blasted the fair fame of any female<lb/>
               whatever - That he had not lived in the practice<lb/>
               of any sin - and that the sufferings and trials of<lb/>
               this life of which he had borne many, were wisely<lb/>
               ordained by providence both as trials of what we<lb/>
               could bear - and as means of weaning us from<lb/>
               the love of this world.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               Yet when he said his he had not a thought that<lb/>
               his latter end was so near - Recovery - and the<lb/>
               hope of spending the next winter at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Naples_IT">Naples</placeName> were<lb/>
               uppermost in his mint till within the last<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back> </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
