<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Maria-Edgeworth-Letters-Project/me-tei/refs/heads/main/melp.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"
    ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter from Walter Scott to Maria Edgeworth, 1829</title>
            <author>Walter Scott</author>
            <editor>Alexandra LaGrand</editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>Wake Forest University, University of Tennessee, Xavier University, Texas
               A&amp;M University</sponsor>
            <principal>Susan Egenolf, Meredith Hale, Hilary Havens, Jessica Richard, and Robin Runia</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Alexandra LaGrand</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2024-05-17">May 17, 20</date>
            </edition>
            <respStmt>
               <orgName type="naf">National Library of Scotland</orgName>
               <resp> photos include: Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page01.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page02.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page03.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page04.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page05.jpg, Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page06.jpg</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</authority>
            <date>2022</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80044899">National Library of Scotland</orgName>
               </p>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 (CC BY 4.0) Unported License</licence>
            </availability>
            <idno>Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Maria Edgeworth Letters Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>National Library of Scotland</repository>
                  <collection/>
                  <idno/>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from 
                  <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW1">
                     <forename>Walter</forename>
                     <surname>Scott</surname>
                  </persName>
                  to <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Maria Edgeworth</persName>, <placeName/>, 
                  <date when="1829-01-01"/>
               </head>
               <physDesc/>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Edgeworth’s spelling and punctuation are retained in transcription, including non-standard spelling, line breaks, and hyphenation of words. The long s and ligatured forms are silently emended.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <correspDesc>
            <correspAction type="sent">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW1">Walter Scott</persName>
            </correspAction>
            <correspAction type="received">
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Maria Edgeworth</persName>
            </correspAction>
         </correspDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2024-05-17" who="Id_who">Created file for letter, encoded letter</change>
         <change when="2024-05-23" who="Id_who">Updated transcription for unclear words</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page01.jpg"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  My dear <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeM1">Miss Edgeworth</persName>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               I have had your letter for several days and only <choice>
                  <orig>an=<lb/>
               swer</orig>
                  <reg>answer</reg>
               </choice> just now not you may believe from what of interest in<lb/>
               the contents but from the odd circumstance of being so <del/>much<lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>aflicted</orig>
                  <reg>afflicted</reg>
               </choice> with chill blains in the fingers that my pen<lb/>
               scrambles every way but the right one: Assuredly I should secure<lb/>
               the character of a most crabbed fellow from these modern<lb/>
               sages who judge of a man from his <choice>
                  <orig>hand writing</orig>
                  <reg>handwriting</reg>
               </choice>. But as<lb/>
               an old man becomes twice a child I must expect I suppose<lb/>
               measles &amp; <choice>
                  <orig>small pox</orig>
                  <reg>smallpox</reg>
               </choice> I only wish I could get a first set<lb/>
               of teeth. To tell you the truth I feel the advance of age more<lb/>
               than I like though my general health is excellent but<lb/>
               I am not able to walk as I did and I fear I could not now<lb/>
               visit <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#St-Kevins-Bed_IE">Saint <choice>
                     <orig>Kevans</orig>
                     <reg>Kevin's</reg>
                  </choice> bed</placeName> This is a great affliction to one<lb/>
               who has been so active as I have been in spite of all <choice>
                  <orig>disad=<lb/>
               vantages</orig>
                  <reg>disadvantages</reg>
               </choice> I must now have a friendly arm instead of<lb/>
               relying on my own exertions and it is sad to think I<lb/>
               shall be worse before I am better. However the mild<lb/>
               weather may help me in some degree &amp; the worst is<lb/>
               a quiet perry (I use to detest a quiet perry) as perhaps<lb/>
               a garden chair<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               All this does not prevent my sincere sympathy in<lb/>
               the increase of your family happiness which I hope <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeF3">Miss Fannys</persName>
               <lb/>
               marriage will afford to herself to you and all who love her<lb/>
               I have not had the same opportunity to know her merits<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page02.jpg"/>
               those of my friends <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeH1">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Butler</persName> and<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#EdgeS1">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi>. Fox</persName>
               <del>Lane</del> But I saw<lb/>
               enough of her (being your sister) when at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Dublin_IE">Dublin</placeName> to feel most<lb/>
               sincerely interested in a young person whose exterior is so amiable<lb/>
               and I am sure she must partake of the talents and <del/> good<lb/>
               feelings of her sisters to deserve the kindest and best wishes<lb/>
               of a friend of your family on the present interesting occasion<lb/>
               In <persName ref="./Personography.xml#WilsL1">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilson</persName> you describe the national character <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BullJ1">John Bull</persName>
               <lb/>
               who is not the worst of three natures though he has not the greater<lb/>
               feeling and rich <choice>
                  <orig>humour</orig>
                  <reg>humor</reg>
               </choice> of your countrymen nor the shrewd <unclear>sagacity</unclear>
               <lb/>
               <del>of <unclear/>
                  <add>
                     <unclear/>
                  </add>
               </del> or the <del/> romantic spirit of thinking and adventuring<lb/>
               which <add>
                  <unclear/>
               </add> the Scotch often conceal under their apparent coldness and which you<lb/>
               have so well painted in that of <title ref="./Workography.xml#Ennui1">M<hi rend="superscript">c</hi>Leod in <unclear>ennui</unclear>
               </title> Depend and<lb/>
               I will find <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Russell-Square_ENK">Russell Square</placeName> when I go to <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#London_ENK">London</placeName> were I be here a vessel<lb/>
               of discovery to make it out and it will be <persName ref="./Personography.xml#WilsL1">M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> Wilsons</persName> fault if we do<lb/>
               not make an internal-acquaintance.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               I had the pleasure of receiving your <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#US">American</placeName> friend <persName ref="./Personography.xml#CrugH1">Miss Douglas</persName>
               <lb/>
               who seems a most ingenuous person She is sad want however of<lb/>
               some one to teach her some points of tact in society which are<lb/>
               necessary to regulate the best feelings and to correct the enthusiasm<lb/>
               of <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#CO">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>Columbian</orig>
                     <reg>Colombian</reg>
                  </choice>
               </placeName> independence. But I was as kind and civil<lb/>
               to her as her time and my own permitted me to be and I hope<lb/>
               I was successful in making her happy during her short visit<lb/>
               at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Abbotsford-House_STK">abbotsford</placeName> for I was <choice>
                  <orig>compelld</orig>
                  <reg>compelled</reg>
               </choice> to leave her to pay suit &amp; service<lb/>
               at the circuit<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               The mention of the Circuit brings me to the horrors which you<lb/>
               have so well described and which resemble nothing so much<lb/>
               as a wild dream. Certainly I thought like you that the <choice>
                  <orig>publick</orig>
                  <reg>public</reg>
               </choice>
               <lb/>
               alarm was but an exaggeration of vulgar <choice>
                  <orig>rumour</orig>
                  <reg>rumor</reg>
               </choice> but the tragedy<lb/>
               is too true &amp; I look in vain for a remedy of the evils though it<lb/>
               easy to see them in which this black &amp; unnatural business<lb/>
               has found its accursed origin<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               The principal source certainly originates in the feelings<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page03.jpg"/>
               of attachment which the Scotch have for their deceased friends &amp; they are curious<lb/>
               in the choice of their <add>place</add> of <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>sepuhlre</orig>
                     <reg>sepulchre</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> and a common <unclear>shepherd</unclear> is often at Whateve<lb/>
               ruinous <choice>
                  <orig>expence</orig>
                  <reg>expense</reg>
               </choice> to his family transported many miles to some <choice>
                  <orig>favoured</orig>
                  <reg>favored</reg>
               </choice> place<lb/>
               of <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>sepuhlre</orig>
                     <reg>sepulchre</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> which has been occupied by his fathers It follows of course<lb/>
               that any interference with their remains <del>are</del>
               <add>is</add> considered <del>th</del> with most<lb/>
               utter horror &amp; indignation To each of their super<add>r</add>iors as they live from clan<lb/>
               ship or habits of dependence, they attach the same feeling of attachment<lb/>
               I experienced it when I had a great domestic loss for I learned <choice>
                  <orig>after<lb/>
               ward</orig>
                  <reg>afterward</reg>
               </choice> that the cemetery was guarded, out of good will by the<lb/>
               servants and <choice>
                  <orig>dependants</orig>
                  <reg>dependents</reg>
               </choice> who had been attached to her during life and<lb/>
               were I to be laid beside <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotM1">my lost companion</persName> just now I have no doubt it would<lb/>
               be long before my humble friends would discontinue the same watch over my<lb/>
               remains and that it would incur mortal <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>risque</orig>
                     <reg>risk</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear> to approach them with<lb/>
               the purpose of violation. This is on a kind and virtuous principle which<lb/>
               every one so far partakes that although an unprejudiced person would<lb/>
               have no <del>
                  <unclear/>
               </del> objections to the idea of his own remains undergoing dissection<lb/>
               if their being exposed to scientific research could be of the least service to<lb/>
               humanity yet we all shudder at the exposure of any who had<lb/>
               been dear to us especially a wife or sister being subjected to a scalpel<lb/>
               among a gazing and unfeeling crowd of students - One would<lb/>
               fight and die to prevent it - This current of feeling is encouraged by the<lb/>
               law which as distinguishing murderers and other atrocious criminals orders<lb/>
               that their bodies should be given for <choice>
                  <orig>publick</orig>
                  <reg>public</reg>
               </choice> dissection. This makes it <choice>
                  <orig>al=<lb/>
               most</orig>
                  <reg>almost</reg>
               </choice> impossible to assign <choice>
                  <orig>publickly</orig>
                  <reg>publicly</reg>
               </choice> the bodies of those who die in<lb/>
               the <choice>
                  <orig>publick</orig>
                  <reg>public</reg>
               </choice> hospitals to the same fate for it would <unclear>bring</unclear> inflicting<lb/>
               on poverty the penalty which wisely or unwisely the <del>same</del> law of the<lb/>
               <del>court</del> country has denounced against guilt of the highest degree &amp; it<lb/>
               would assuredly deprive all who have a remaining spark of feeling or<lb/>
               shame, of the benefit of those consolations of charity of which they<lb/>
               are the best objects. This <unclear>natural</unclear> prejudice <unclear/>deeply seated<lb/>
               to be eradicated. If not very liberal, it is surely natural <unclear/> of the<lb/>
               best feelings must be destroyed ere it can be eradicated What then<lb/>
               remains - The only <unclear>idea</unclear> I see is to permit importatation from other <choice>
                  <orig>coun<lb/>
               tries</orig><reg>countries</reg>
               </choice>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page04.jpg"/>
               countries If a subject can be hard in <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Paris_FR">Paris</placeName> for 10 or 20 franks it will surely<lb/>
               pay the importer who brings it to <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#STK">Scotland</placeName> &amp; if the medical<unclear>men</unclear> find<lb/>
               it convenient to use more economy they will teach anatomy <del>g</del> in all<lb/>
               surgical purposes equally will though they may not make such advances<lb/>
               in physiology. Something must be done for there is an end of the Cantabit<lb/>
               vacuus the last prerogative of beggary which entitled him to laugh at the <unclear>
                  <choice>
                     <orig>risque</orig><reg>risk</reg>
                  </choice>
               </unclear>
               <lb/>
               of robbery. the veriest wretch in the highway may be better booty than<lb/>
               a person of consideration since the last <del>has</del> may have but a few shillings<lb/>
               in his pocket and the beggar being once dead is worth ten pounds to his<lb/>
               murderer<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               The great number of the lower Irish which have come over here since<lb/>
               the peace is like all important occurrences attended with its own share<lb/>
               of good and evil. It must relieve <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#IE">Ireland</placeName> in part of the excess of population<lb/>
               which is one of its greatest evils and it accommodates <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#STK">Scotland</placeName>
               <del>into</del> with<lb/>
               a race of hardy and indefatigable <choice>
                  <orig>labourers</orig>
                  <reg>laborers</reg>
               </choice> without which it would<lb/>
               impossible to carry on the very expensive improvements which have been<lb/>
               executed Our canals our railrods and our various public works are all<lb/>
               wrought by Irish I have often employed them myself at burning clay<lb/>
               and similar operations - I have found these <choice>
                  <orig>labourers</orig>
                  <reg>laborers</reg>
               </choice> quiet and<lb/>
               tractable light-spirited too, and <del/>happy to a degree beyond <choice>
                  <orig>be<lb/>
               -lief</orig>
                  <reg>belief</reg>
               </choice> and in no <add>degree</add> quarrelsome Keep whisky from them and them from<lb/>
               whisky - But most unhappily for all parties they work at far too<lb/>
               <add>low</add> a rate, at a rate in short, which can but just procure salt and <choice>
                  <orig>po-<lb/>
               tatoes</orig>
                  <reg>potatoes</reg>
               </choice> They become reckless of course of all the comforts and decencies<lb/>
               of life which they have no means of procuring Extreme poverty brings<lb/>
               ignorance and vice and these are the mothers of crime If <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#IE">Ireland</placeName>
               <lb/>
               were to submit to some kind of poor rate (I do not mean that of<lb/>
               <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#ENK">England</placeName>) but something that should secure to the indigent their<lb/>
               natural share of the fruits of the earth and might enable them<lb/>
               at least to feed while others are feasting it would apparently <unclear>raise</unclear>
               <lb/>
               the character of the lower-orders, and deprive them of that <choice>
                  <orig>reckless<lb/>
               ness</orig>
                  <reg>recklessness</reg>
               </choice> of futurity which leads them to think only of the present. Indeed<lb/>
               where intoxication of the lower ranks is mentioned as a vice we<lb/>
               must<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page05.jpg"/>
               allow the<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               temptation is well nigh inevitable Meat clothes, fire all that men<lb/>
               can and do want are supplied by <add>a</add> drop of whisky, and no one<lb/>
               should be surprised that the relief (too often the only one within<lb/>
               the wretches power) is eagerly grasped at. We pay back I suspect<lb/>
               the inconveniences we receive from the character of our Irish <choice>
                  <orig>impor<lb/>
               tation</orig>
                  <reg>importation</reg>
               </choice> by sending you a set of <choice>
                  <orig>half educated</orig>
                  <reg>half-educated</reg>
               </choice>, <choice>
                  <orig>cold hearted</orig>
                  <reg>cold-hearted</reg>
               </choice>
               <lb/>
               Scotchmen to be agents and middlemen Among them too, there are<lb/>
               good and excellent characters yet I can conceive they often <choice>
                  <orig>mis<lb/>
               lead</orig>
                  <reg>mislead</reg>
               </choice> their English employers.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               I am no great believer in the extreme degree of <del>inform</del> improvement<lb/>
               to be derived from the advancement of science for every pursuit of that<lb/>
               nature tends when pushed to a certain extent to harden the heart &amp;<lb/>
               render the philosopher reckless of every thing save the objects of his<lb/>
               own pursuit; all equilibrium in the character is destroyed and<lb/>
               the visual nerve of the understanding is perverted by being fixed<lb/>
               on one object exclusively. Thus we see theological sects (although<lb/>
               inculcating the moral doctrines) are eternally placing man’s zeal<lb/>
               in opposition to them &amp; even in the calling it is astonishing how<lb/>
               we become callous to right and wrong when the question is to gain<lb/>
               or lose a cause &amp; I have myself often wondered how I became so<lb/>
               indifferent to the horrors of a criminal trial <del>In</del> if it involved a<lb/>
               point of law In like manner the pursuit of physical studies <choice>
                  <orig>in<lb/>
               flicts</orig>
                  <reg>inflicts</reg>
               </choice> tortures on the lower animals of creation and at length<lb/>
               comes to rub shoulders against the <unclear>West Port</unclear>. The state of high<lb/>
               <choice>
                  <orig>civilisation</orig>
                  <reg>civilization</reg>
               </choice> to which we have arrived, is perhaps scarcely a<lb/>
               national blessing since while the <hi rend="underline">few</hi> are improved to the highest<lb/>
               point the many are in proportion tantalized and degraded &amp;<lb/>
               the same nation displays at the same time the very highest and the<lb/>
               very lowest state in which the human race can exist in point of<lb/>
               intellect. Here is a <persName ref="./Personography.xml#KnoxR1">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               </persName> who is able to take down the whole clock work<lb/>
               of the human frame &amp; may in <unclear>time</unclear> find some way of repairing<lb/>
               and putting it together again and <hi rend="underline">there</hi> is <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BurkW1">Burke</persName> with the body<lb/>
               <note>Here, Scott is referring to the Burke and Hare murders. These murders were a string of sixteen killings where Burke and Hare killed and sold corpses to Dr. Knox for medical dissection.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="Edgeworth_NLS_23130_1829_page06.jpg"/>
               murdered countrywoman on his back &amp; her blood on his hands<lb/>
               asking his price for the body <del/>from the learned carcass<lb/>
               butcher. After all the Golden Age was the period for general hap<lb/>
               piness when the Earth gave its <unclear>stores</unclear> Without <choice>
                  <orig>labour</orig>
                  <reg>labor</reg>
               </choice> and the<lb/>
               people <del>were</del>existed only in the numbers which it could easily<lb/>
               subsist but this was too good to last As our numbers increased our<lb/>
               wants multiplied and here we are contending with increasing<lb/>
               difficulties by the force of repeated inventions. Whether we shall<lb/>
               at last eat each other as of yore, or whether the earth will get a<lb/>
               flap with a comets tail first <del/> who but the <persName ref="./Personography.xml#IrviE1">reverend M<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
                  <lb/>
               Irving</persName> will venture to pronounce.<lb/>
               Now here is a fearful long letter and the next thing<lb/>
               is to send under <persName ref="./Personography.xml#LeveG1">Lord Levesen Gowers</persName> omnipotent frank.<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotA1">Anne</persName> sends best compliments she says she had the honour to<lb/>
               despatch her congratulations to you already. <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotW4">Walter</persName> and his<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#ScotJ1">little wife</persName> are at <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Nice_FR">Nice</placeName> He is now Major of his Regiment, which<lb/>
               is rapid advancement &amp; so has gone abroad to see the world.<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#LockJ1">Lockhart</persName> has been here for a week but is now gone for England I<lb/>
               suspect he is at this moment stopped by the snow storm and <choice>
                  <orig>so<lb/>
               =lacing</orig>
                  <reg>solacing</reg>
               </choice> himself with a cigar <del/>somewhere in <placeName ref="./Placeography.xml#Northumberland_ENK">
                  <choice>
                     <orig>North<lb/>
               humberland</orig>
                     <reg>Northumberland</reg>
                  </choice>
               </placeName>. That is all the news that can interest you<lb/>
               <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrewD1">D<hi rend="superscript">r</hi>
               </persName> and <persName ref="./Personography.xml#BrewM1">M<hi rend="superscript">rs</hi> Brewster</persName> are rather getting over their heavy loss<lb/>
               but it is still too visible on their brows and that broad river lying<lb/>
               daily before them is a cruel remembrancer I saw a brother of<lb/>
               yours on a visit there, he dined with us one day and promised to<lb/>
               come and see us which I hope he will make good My pen has<lb/>
               been declaring itself independent this half hour which is the<lb/>
               more unnatural as it is engaged in writing to its <del/>former<lb/>
               mistress<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back/>
   </text>
</TEI>
